在罗马全境立起您的雕像
Statues of you across the empire.
我还在想神殿里也该立一座
We will have one in the temple.
我们应该预估
We should assume
全境叛乱的情况
there'll be a full-scale rebellion.
我们说的可是神殿的毁灭!
This is about the destruction of the temple!
约亚拿 谢谢你指引我走向耶稣
Thank you, Joanna, for leading me to Jesus.
大比大!
Tabitha!
所有罗马的敌人...
All enemies of Rome...
都会受到惩罚以及镇压
are punished and crushed.
- 你是?  - 埃塞俄比亚女王的银库总管
- And you are? - Chief Treasurer to the Queen of Ethiopia.
你告诉这个埃塞俄比亚人
You tell this Ethiopian
我们很荣幸
that we would be honored to entertain
款待贵宾
such an important visitor.
那可憎之物即将到此...
Soon the abomination will be here...
一座将掀起血雨腥风的雕像
A statue that heralds eternal war.
你难道不懂我们需要联合
Do you not see that we need to unite
抗击这个庞然大怪?
to fight this monstrosity?
我们不是敌人 雅各
We aren't enemies, James.
若果真如此 那就不要再迫害我们
If this is true, stop persecuting us.
也许这就是结局
This could be the end.
本片涉及圣经内容的名词 段落 均参照和合本翻译
公元: 圣经续 第一季第11集
这个神殿不只是凡人的双手堆起来的
This temple is not just bricks and mortar
砖头和灰泥
built by the hands of men.
这是神在人间的屋子
It is the house of God on earth,
他的家
his home,
最神圣的地方
the Holy of Holies.
而它受到了威胁
And it's under threat.
--==圣城家园SCG字幕组 http://hdscg.com/==--
仅供翻译交流使用, 禁止用于商业用途
协调&校对: 影子
翻译: 小黄不小黄 猫呗
翻译: 鸟生鱼汤 舒大卷子 AU薇
几天之后
Within days,
一座罗马大帝的雕像
a statue of the Roman Emperor
就会到达耶路撒冷
will arrive in Jerusalem.
他命令将其放在神殿里面
He demands it be placed inside the temple
让我们去朝拜它
and that we should worship it.
放在这里
Put it here.
如果上帝的居所被这样的东西亵渎
If God's house is defiled by this abomination,
他就会离开
he will remove himself.
他就会离开这座神殿 离开我们
He will leave the temple, and he will leave us.
我们的尸体就会腐烂
Our crops will rot and fail.
到处会充满饥荒和瘟疫
Famine and plague will dance upon the land.
我们的孩子们会挨饿
Our children will starve.
我们的敌人们会因为我们的虚弱而欢欣鼓舞
Our enemies will delight in our weakness,
我们在对抗他们的时候将无依无靠
and we shall be helpless to oppose them.
我们不能允许这种事发生!
We cannot allow it!
我们不会允许这种事发生!
We will not allow it!
不要停 不要停
Don't stop. Don't stop.
不要让他们有理由来查
Don't give them a reason to look.
请尝尝吧
Please, uh, help yourself.
很不错 对吧?
Good, huh?
所以我现在和你们说
That is why I speak to you now.
我们一定要联合起来保护神殿
We must come together to protect the temple.
所有的党派 所有的教派 所有的城镇 所有的区域...
Every sect, every creed, every town, every region...
我们必须要把分歧放到一边
We must set aside our differences.
现在我们需要的是兄弟情义和团结!
Now is the time for brotherhood and unity!
让十万人用一个声音说话!
To let 100,000 speak with one voice!
我们支持你 大祭司
We stand with you, high priest.
去找你们的同胞!
Go to your people!
让他们来支持神殿!
Call them to stand with the temple!
有谣言说
There are rumors
这座雕像是纯金的
that this statue is made of pure gold.
显然 大帝的虚荣心真是没有止境
Clearly, there are no limits to this Emperor's vanity.
你应该感激
You should be grateful.
他的狂妄自大让整座城市为之愤怒
His arrogance will enrage the city
并让上千的人加入我们
and bring thousands more to the cause.
我很幸运 可以在这里帮忙
It is fortunate that I am here and able to help.
这不只是偶然
That's not just chance.
这是上帝的旨意
It is God's will.
我们注定会成功
We are ordained to succeed.
是的 我相信
Yes. I believe we are.
当我的女王知道我的作为
And my Queen will be thrilled
她一定会很兴奋的
when she learns what I have done.
我们的胜利不光可以让埃塞俄比亚人庆祝
Our victory will be celebrated not just in Ethiopia.
我们会给世界以反抗的信心
We will give the rest of the world confidence to fight back.
我们点起了一团火 将会把罗马烧成灰烬
We are lighting a fire that will burn Rome to cinders.
你做的已经够多了
You've done enough.
寡妇们一会儿会来收的
The widows will collect these later.
她们让我感谢你的帮忙
They asked me to thank you for your charity.
但我还没干完呢
But I'm not finished.
你的伤口太严重了 大比大
Your wounds are too raw, Tabitha.
你失血过多
You're losing too much blood.
你一定要休息
You must rest.
我感觉好多了
I feel much better.
这让我感觉我在做贡献
And this makes me feel that I'm contributing.
请休息吧
Please rest.
我很喜欢这个
I enjoy it.
我负责缝缝补补
I have my sewing,
让男人们去聊
and the men have their very long
那些重要的事情
and very important conversations.
他们都站起来 为大祭司喝彩
They were all on their feet, cheering the high priest.
我在听他说的时候 我...
And as I listened to him, I...
原谅我 但我实在忍不住想象
Well, forgive me, but I couldn't help but imagine
是我站在他的位置上
it was myself in his place,
谈论耶稣基督
but I was talking about Jesus Christ.
你能想象这对我们有何意义吗?
Can you see what that could be like for all of us?
想象一下可以说他的名字而不用害怕
Imagine being able to speak his name without fear.
是的 是 不止这些
Yes. Yes, and more than that.
想象我们可以从内部影响犹太公会
Imagine being able to influence the Sanhedrin from within.
不需要躲在暗处 不再轻声说他的名字
No more hiding in the dark, no more whispering his name.
你们觉得如何?
Well, what do you say, hmm?
你觉得该亚法会把这一切给你吗?
And you really think Caiaphas is going to give you all this?
是的
Yes.
那他会要求什么作报偿呢?
And what will he want in return?
呃 我们俩可以和他谈判
Well, we will negotiate, you and I.
我不去
Not me.
我不会和杀了耶稣的人说话
Not with the man that killed Jesus.
彼得 这是我们把耶稣的教
Peter, this is our chance
传播开来的机会
to take the church of Jesus forward.
不 我得保护你们 不受他的伤害
Oh, no. I have to keep you all safe, away from him.
我们不需要神殿
We don't need the temple.
至少让我和他谈谈
Let me at least speak to him.
我不是新手了 我会向他施压
I am no novice. I will press him hard.
我不会再否定我们的主了!
I will not deny our Lord again!
嘿 罗马猪!
Hey, Roman pigs!
等等 等等 等等
Hold, hold, hold, hold, hold.
他们只是小孩
They're just boys.
继续走
Move on.
兄弟们!
My brothers!
兄弟们 你们来此
My brothers, you have come
因你们知道 上帝召唤你们
because you know that God calls upon you
来对抗这卑劣之徒 保卫他的神殿
to defend his temple against this abomination.
我们将替天行道
We will unleash a righteous wave
将这神殿腐败的祭司净化驱除
that will cleanse the temple of its corrupt priesthood
把我们土地上所有罗马的印记洗涤而去!
and wash every last trace of Rome from our lands!
埃塞俄比亚给了我们武器
Ethiopia has given us weapons
也给了我们自制武器的能力
and the means to make our own.
我们便有手段铲除这罗马病毒
We have the implements to cut out this Roman infection.
却仍缺虔诚之手处置他们
But we need pious hands to put them into,
就是你们的手
your hands.
你们愿与我们一起吗?
So, are you with us?
我看到该亚法派出他的小喽啰来当间谍
I see Caiaphas has sent his little rodent to spy.
不是
No.
我被派来传达消息
I've been sent with a message.
大祭司发来邀请
The high priest extends an invitation
以讨论如何继续共同合作
to discuss how we proceed together.
骗子
Liar.
把他带走!
Take him away!
我想增加耶路撒冷周围巡逻人数
I'd like to increase the number of patrols around Jerusalem.
派人上街巡逻已经是一种挑衅了
Putting men on the streets is an act of provocation.
我们在组织势力 不是军队
W... we're a holding force, not an army.
很多人都会帮助隐瞒这个事实
More men will help hide this fact.
很好
Very well.
增加一倍巡逻人数
Double the number of patrols.
我们能挺过去的
We'll get through this.
每次都能挺过去
We always do.
这个痛苦的城市...
This miserable city...
看看你
Look at you.
你什么都没吃
You haven't touched your food.
百夫长的担心毫无意义
The centurion's worries don't help.
我能帮上忙吗?
Is there anything I can do?
说出来 我一定做到
Name it and it's done.
确实有些事
Perhaps there is something.
那个拿撒勒女人 约亚拿...
The Nazarene woman, Joanna...
放了她
Release her.
这个女人和你有什么利害关系?
What is your interest in this woman?
只是同情罢了
Only one of empathy.
同情使人软弱 克劳迪娅
Empathy breeds weakness, Claudia.
我们并不软弱
And we are not weak.
我关心她怎么...
I don't see how my showing concern...
你不软弱
You are not weak.
你听懂了吗?
Do you understand me?
我让你失望了
I've upset you.
没有
No.
你的话很有道理
Your words make a lot of sense.
我太鲁莽了
I've been too bold.
你... 你才是磐石
You... you are the rock.
你顾虑我们的安危...
Your concern for our safety...
雅各 拜托
James, please.
除了比我能说会道 你什么都没做错
You've done nothing wrong except speak better than I can.
也找不到比你更好的人来为我们的事业斗争
And we could not hope for anyone better to fight our cause.
我只想让这迫害结束
I only want an end to the persecution.
我忘不了那人对耶稣的所作所为
I cannot forget what that man did to Jesus.
耶稣在十字架上时
When Jesus was on the cross,
痛苦太过剧烈
when the pain was so great
他的身体扭曲 颤抖
that his body would contort and shake,
他痛声疾呼"父啊 赦免他们
he cried out, "Father, forgive them,
因为他们所作的 他们不晓得"
for they know not what they do."
如果他让上帝原谅他们
If he asks it of God,
也会让我们原谅
then he asks it of us, too.
一定会的
Yes, of course.
雅各会和大祭司交涉
James will talk to the high priest,
他会见证我们所受迫害的终结
and we will finally see an end to our persecution.
我们一起去
Let's go together.
不 我去没有用
No. My presence won't help.
那你告诉我什么条件你才肯去
Then tell me what terms you'll accept.
我对你的判断有信心 上帝会指引你
I have faith in your judgment, and God will guide you.
但是我必须离开耶路撒冷
But I must leave Jerusalem.
你要去哪?
Well, where are you going?
去外面
Out there.
去传教
To preach.
大祭司 我必须提醒你别忘了自己的承诺...
High priest, I must remind you of your own pledge...
停止对那些追随耶稣之人的
An end to the persecution and arrest
迫害和追捕
of those who follow Jesus.
必须马上停止
It must stop immediately.
你在和我谈条件吗?
You're setting conditions for me?
很好
Very well.
我现在就结束
I end it now.
谢谢
Thank you.
那么这一定意味着我们可以公开传教
It must surely follow that we be free to preach openly.
允许传教 但是有限制
There are limits to what's acceptable.
罗马人是很咬文嚼字的
The Romans are a very literal people.
只要把任何提及国王的事当真
They take any mention of kings at face value
他们就管这叫煽动
and call it sedition.
说耶稣是国王 还危及神殿
Saying Jesus is a king endangers the temple.
我们会小心的
Then we'll be cautious.
你们也不要说他是弥赛亚
And you'll refrain from saying he's the Messiah.
但这是事实
But that is the truth.
你们的事实会激怒很多人
Your truth will offend many.
我可能就没法保护你们了
And I may not be able to protect you.
我们希望能进入神殿并获得尊敬
We wish to sit in the temple and win respect,
不想冒犯任何人
not offend anyone.
但也不想删改我们传的教
But we will not be censored.
他就是弥赛亚
He is the Messiah.
你对自己的要求一点也不羞愧吗?
You're not shy in your requests, are you?
他是上帝之子
He is the son of God.
他是复活之人
He is resurrected.
他会回来的
And he will return.
好吧 既然说服不了你...
Well, if you will not be persuaded otherwise...
我不会被说服的
I won't.
那就这样吧
Then let it be so.
我相信以后 你们会记住
I trust you will remember my generosity
我的慷慨大方
in the days to come.
成功了
Success.
允许我们回神殿了?
We're allowed back?
是的
We are.
- 进来吧  - 来吧
- Come in.  - Come.
施舍点给穷人吧
Alms for the poor.
谢谢你
Thank you.
大比大?
Tabitha?
来人帮帮我!
Somebody help me!
我们得把她带回家里去
We need to get her back to the house.
玛丽 很抱歉
I'm sorry, Mary.
我应该听你的
I should have listened to you.
不 没事的 我在这里
No, don't worry. I'm here.
玛丽 带我回约帕吧 去见我的家人
Mary, take me home to my family, to Joppa.
求你了 在我死之前一定要再见他们一次
Please, I have to see them again before I die.
你有可能撑不到那么远
I'm not sure you'll get that far.
但我们一定要去
We have to.
那就快点启程吧
Then let's hurry up.
我来帮你扶着她
I'll help you take her.
不 必须我来
No. I must do it.
这是我的错
This is my fault.
因为我 他们会处决约亚拿
Because of me, they're going to execute Joanna.
我不能再失去大比大
I can't lose Tabitha, too.
约亚拿... 你还受得了吗?
Is it... tolerable, Joanna?
这是上帝的意愿
It's God's will.
我相信他
I trust in him.
这个 我 呃...
Please, I, um...
你得吃点东西来保持体力
You need to eat to keep your strength up.
谢谢你
Thank you.
你的丈夫决定什么时候行刑了吗?
Has your husband decided when it will be done?
并不是所有事都由他决定
He doesn't get to decide everything.
停下
Stop there.
罗马人的走狗
Roman pigs.
放松
Relax.
并且 他们找错了马车
Besides, they are looking in the wrong carts.
你看到他们的人手越来越多了吗?
You've seen how they've increased their numbers?
这很正常
It's only natural.
他们感受到了威胁
They feel threatened.
坐吧
Sit.
你来干什么
What do you want?
利未让我来的
Levi sent me.
他担心你太... 抛头露面了
He's concerned you're too... visible.
为什么?
Why?
我没跟大家融为一体吗?
Do I not blend in?
那也没有必要故意吸引别人的注意
Still, there is no sense in drawing attention to yourself,
在这里更不行
here of all places.
我来给你解释一下
Let me explain something to you.
我是一个来访的贵宾 理应被看见
I am a visiting dignitary here to be seen.
我没什么可隐藏 也没有见不得人的事
I have nothing to hide, no hidden agenda.
但当我从人们面前消失的时候
But the moment I disappear from view,
就会引起别人的注意
then I draw attention to myself
然后他们就会开始怀疑
and they begin to ask questions.
所以 只要我在公开场合 就没人能把我怎么样
So, when I am visible, I am untouchable.
现在 让我们讨论一下你们的责任
Now, let us consider your responsibilities,
可以吗?
shall we?
那个神殿的间谍会让我的日子很不好过
The temple spy could make my life very uncomfortable.
你们能保证他不会造成麻烦吗?
Do I have your assurance that he will not be a problem?
在这里? 给秃鹫喂食吗?
Out here? For the vultures?
那么让我先向上帝祷告
Then let me make my peace with God.
以色列 听啊
Hear, O Israel.
耶和华是我们的神
The Lord is our God.
够了!
Enough!
愿他荣耀之国的名
Blessed be the name of his glorious kingdom
- 长存不朽  - 够了 听见没!
- forever and ever.  - Enough, I said!
你要爱耶和华 你的上帝 与所有...
You shall love the Lord, your God, with all...
大祭司!
High priest!
把我的医生叫来
Bring my physician.
坐下 就这样
Sit. That's it.
事情比我们想的还要严重
Things are far worse than we imagined.
他能活下来吗?
Will he live?
他确定他看见了什么?
And he's certain of what he saw?
埃塞俄比亚人的武器?
Ethiopian weapons?
那些狂热分子本来只敢想 现在他们敢做了
The zealots have the will, and now they have the means.
他们会把这场危机变成战争
They will turn this crisis into war.
我知道他们会尝试 但从没想过他们有这个能力
I knew that they'd try, but I never thought they'd be able.
我们必须去找彼拉多
We must go to Pilate,
告诉他那些人的计划
tell him about their plans,
让他去处理
let him deal with them.
我们不能
We can't.
我们会被当成同谋的
We'll be damned as collaborators.
在他们眼里 我们已经跟他们是同谋了
In their eyes, we already are collaborators.
狂热分子们想置我们于死地 难道你没看出来?
The zealots want us dead. Can't you see?
我会控制他们
So I control them.
太晚了
It's too late.
他们已经有武器了
They already have weapons.
而这次反抗绝不会成功
And this revolt will never succeed.
罗马会将其镇压 连同我们一起
Rome will crush it and crush us with it.
这你是知道的
And you know that.
去找彼拉多
Go to Pilate.
把这座城市从罗马人的屠杀中拯救出来
Save this city from a Roman massacre.
你在建议我们打开大门
Are you suggesting that we open the doors
允许神庙被玷污吗?
and allow the temple to be defiled?
上帝会暂时离开神庙 没错
God will leave the temple for a time, yes.
而我们也会承担后果
And we will suffer in his absence.
但上帝会听见我们的祈祷
But he will hear our prayers,
假以时日
and in time,
神庙会被净化 上帝也会回来
the temple will be cleansed and God will return.
不
No.
绝不
Never.
绝不!
Never!
我不会成为让上帝
I refuse to be the high priest
离我们而去的大祭司
who allowed God to abandon us.
绝不!
Never!
犹太的未来或未可知
The future of Judea is uncertain,
但我带来了上帝的信息
but I bring you God's message.
以耶稣基督之名
Salvation will be found
你们会找到救赎
in the name of Jesus Christ.
腓利
Philip.
你怎么来这里了?
What brings you here?
我以为你在耶路撒冷
I thought you'd be in Jerusalem.
我本来想回去找你们的
I was coming back to be with you all.
但你一直都做得很好...
But you've been doing so well...
你在撒玛利亚的作为
Your work in Samaria.
更多的人开始追随耶稣
Many more have come to Jesus.
但我怎么可能忽略耶路撒冷呢?
But how can I ignore Jerusalem?
那是我们的家 是所有这一切的中心
It's our home, the center of everything.
耶稣告诉我们把他的信息
Jesus told us to spread his word
传播到世界的每个角落
to the ends of the earth.
你的传教至关重要
Your work is vital.
那么 我现在应该怎么做?
So, what should I do now?
去南边
Go to the south,
那条连接耶路撒冷和加沙的沙漠之路
to the desert road that leads from Jerusalem to Gaza.
我们该出发了
We should go.
立刻
Right now.
去哪儿?
Go where?
去加沙的沙漠之路
The Gaza road.
你在说什么?
What are you talking about?
你没看到天使吗?
You didn't see the angel?
去吧
Go.
按天使的命令去做
Do as the angel commanded.
我会去往约帕继续传教
And I'll press on towards Joppa.
约帕
你到家了 大比大
You're home now, Tabitha.
我还没准备好死去
I'm not ready to die.
我的女儿啊
My daughter.
妈妈
Mother.
她受伤了
She's injured.
在背部
It's her back.
我必须和彼拉多谈谈
I must speak to Pilate.
有什么目的?
To what purpose?
你请求我的帮助
You asked me for my help.
我有一条可以阻止一场大屠杀的消息
I have information that will prevent a massacre.
那为什么要保密不和我说?
Then why the secrecy?
如果你想要我的帮助...
If you want my help...
因为我必须同时背叛我所恨恶的
Because I must betray both those I hate
和我所爱的
and those that I love.
你应该听听她要说什么
I think you need to hear what she has to say.
狂热分子和埃塞俄比亚人结盟了
The zealots have formed an alliance with Ethiopia.
全副武装
They are armed
准备将卡里古拉的雕像作为导火线
and are using Caligula's statue as a catalyst.
计划发动一场巨大的暴动
They plan to launch a huge uprising
来对抗罗马
against Rome.
搜查所有人!
Check everyone!
不要挡在路上! 走开!
Get out of the way! Move! Stand aside!
搜查楼梯!
Check the stairs!
我们被出卖了 快拿!
We are betrayed. Quick!
别管埃塞俄比亚的武器了
Forget the Ethiopian's weapons.
我们自己还有
We still have our own.
开门!
Open up!
搜查屋顶!
Check the rooftop!
他们逃走了 搜查那里!
We missed them. Check there!
列队!
Line up!
跟我走吧
Come with me.
为什么?
To what end?
这到底是什么意思?
What is this nonsense?
我是女王的银库总管
I am my Queen's Chief Treasurer.
任何对我的伤害都是战争行为
Any harm to me would be an act of war.
输入武器才是战争行为
Importing weapons is an act of war.
可能吧
Possibly.
但你不会想要激怒埃塞俄比亚的
But you are in no position to provoke Ethiopia.
你真是一点都不顾忌自己的口气
You have no regard for your tongue.
我只是想提醒你 你的新大帝
I just want to remind you that your new emperor
似乎不太在意这个地方
doesn't seem to care for this region.
只有你一个人在这
You are out here on your own.
这么说 你的女王要冒险攻击帝国 是吗?
So, your Queen would risk an attack on the empire, would she?
她会考虑这种机会
She would relish the opportunity.
我不这么认为
I don't think she would.
我不认为她知道这事 是吗?
I don't think she even knows about this, does she?
你过界了
You've overstepped the mark.
她对我绝对信任
She trusts me implicitly.
那么她对你的失望会更强烈
And so her disappointment in you will be all the greater.
把他的东西拿过来
Bring his things.
外交的确阻止了我杀你
Diplomacy does indeed prevent me from killing you,
但我会写信给你的女王
but I shall write to your Queen.
我想你再也不能回埃塞俄比亚了
I imagine you will never be able to return to Ethiopia again.
在你为了她放弃了那么多之后
And after you'd given up so much for her.
你的人就留在这里当奴隶
Your men shall remain here as slaves to their superiors.
捡起来
Pick it up.
啧 啧 啧!
Tch, tch, tch!
这是什么?
What is this?
来自主教该亚法的一份礼物
It is a gift from the high priest, Caiaphas.
你可以留着 作为你愚蠢的提醒
You may keep it as a reminder of your foolishness.
把这个... 生物赶出我的城市
Remove this... creature from my city.
有些日子我们的信心会被考验到极致
These are days that test our faith to the limit.
当我们感觉到不公正和暴行在心里翻腾
When we feel injustice and outrage churning in our hearts,
罗马士兵充斥着我们的街道
Rome fills our streets with soldiers.
我们还有武器
We still have weapons.
上帝依然支持我们 这是你告诉我的
And God still favors us. You told me so.
是的 你说得对 我们的目标是正义的
Yes, you're right. Our cause is just.
但我不会忘记这些的
But I won't forget this.
罗马人威胁我们的神殿
Rome threatens our temple,
将恐惧阴霾散布在我们城中!
throws a shadow of fear over our city!
但你会寻求到光明和拯救
But you will find light and salvation
以基督耶稣的名义
in the name of Jesus Christ.
说得好
Fine words.
但靠说并不能保护神殿
But words won't protect the temple.
我说过 我忠于我们的目标
I told you I'm loyal to the cause.
当罗马人指控我们时
And when the Romans charge us,
你会手持刀剑
will you still be loyal then,
保持忠诚吗?
with a sword in your hand?
为了区域的持续和平
For the continued peace of the region.
你在干什么?
What are you doing?
我在写一封有意思的小短信给我们亲爱的朋友
I am composing an amusing little note to our dear friend,
伟大的埃塞俄比亚女王
the Great Queen of Ethiopia.
你今天做得很好 克劳迪娅
You did well today, Claudia.
谢谢你
Thank you.
把利亚和她的消息带给你
Having brought Leah to you and her information,
我想知道有没有可能 作为回报
I was wondering if perhaps, as a favor in kind,
你可能会考虑释放那个拿撒勒女人
you might consider releasing the Nazarene woman.
首先 叛乱还没有平息
Firstly, this revolt is still very much alive.
第二
And second,
你理应将消息带给我
you bring information to me as a matter of course,
因为你是我的妻子 这是你的责任
because you are my wife, it is your duty.
但是那...
But that's...
我不想觉得
I would hate to think
你将利亚带来给我仅仅是
that you only brought Leah to me
因为你觉得这样会创造机会时说服我
because you thought you might exploit the opportunity.
我做了正确的事来阻止战争
I did what was right to prevent war.
而你作为我的丈夫 有责任听从我的建议
And you have a duty as my husband to listen to my advice.
她会被处死 克劳迪娅
She will be put to death, Claudia.
她必须被处死
She has to be.
到此为止
And that's the end of it.
重复给我听
Read it back to me.
约亚拿
Joanna.
跟我走
Come with me.
是时候走了
It's time to go.
你要干什么?
What are you doing?
过来
Come.
把门打开
Open the door.
你们知道我是谁 对吧?
You know who I am, don't you?
把门打开
Open the door.
如果你们不开
And if you don't,
你们就得向我丈夫解释不开的理由
you'll have to explain why not to my husband.
你对这个女人的兴趣很反常
Your interest in this woman is unnatural.
她对你做了什么?
What has she done to you?
她什么也没做
She's done nothing.
她欺凌他人 并且扭曲他们的思想
She preys upon others and twists their minds.
她妖言迷惑了那个年轻女裁缝
She poisoned the ear of that young seamstress,
现在她正在对你做同样的事情
and now she's doing the same to you.
不是这样的
No.
我只是觉得让她受折磨是错误的
I just believe it is wrong that she should suffer.
所以你就为一个陌生人而背叛我
And so you would betray me for a stranger.
她对你下了什么咒语?
What spell has she cast upon you?
你为什么要放她逃走 让我蒙羞?
Why would you want to shame me with her escape?
非常好
Very well.
我满足你的愿望
You shall have your wish.
你可以选择现在扼死她
You may choose to set her free now
让她自由
by strangulation
或者让她钉上十字架
or let her go to the cross.
看看她吧
Look at her.
她的一只脚早已踏上了黄泉路上
She's already halfway there.
我们只需轻轻一捏即可
All it takes is a little squeeze.
你这个魔鬼
You're a monster.
你认为自己正在从我手里救她
You think you are trying to save her from me.
但我才是在救你
But I'm trying to save you.
别让我做选择
Don't make me choose.
我会选择的
I will choose.
非常好
Very well.
哥尼流
Cornelius.
以耶稣基督之名 我原谅你
In the name of Christ, I forgive you.
就到此为止吧
This ends here.
你明白吗?
Do you understand?
准备
Prepare.
开始吧
Begin.
"他像羔羊被牵到宰杀之地
"He was led like a sheep to the slaughter.
又像羊在剪毛的人手下无声
As a lamb before his shearer is silent,
他也是这样不开口
so he did not open his mouth.
他卑微的时候 人不按公义审判他
In his humiliation, he was deprived of justice.
谁能述说他的世代
Who shall speak of his descendents?
因为他的生命从地上夺去"
For his life was taken from the earth."
你看起来遇到了困难 朋友
You look to have fallen on hard times, friend.
确实如此
Indeed.
我摔得也很重
And I have fallen hard.
如果你需要帮助的话
If you need help,
我过去修过一些车轮
I've repaired a few wheels in my time.
谢谢
Thank you.
请吧
Please.
你刚刚读的以赛亚书里的那一段...
The passage you were reading just now from Isaiah...
给你带来慰藉了吗?
does it bring you comfort?
我原本希望它可以
I had hoped it would,
但是我理解起来有些困难
but I am struggling to understand it.
先知说的是他自己
Does the prophet speak of himself
还是其他什么人?
or of someone else?
他说的是一个
He's talking of a man
理解了深重苦难和羞辱的人
who knew great suffering and humiliation,
一个教导我们 通过信仰
the man who taught us that, through faith,
就可以在他身上得到拯救的人
we will find salvation in him.
这个人是谁?
Who is this man?
他是耶稣基督
He is Jesus Christ,
神之子
the son of God.
我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
大比大! 非常抱歉
Tabitha! So sorry.
看! 沙漠里的水
Look! Water in the desert.
现在什么能够阻止我受洗
Now what can stop my being baptized
并且把耶稣所说的话传到世界的角落呢?
and taking the word of Jesus into the corners of the world?
你忏悔你的罪行吗?
Do you repent your sins?
我忏悔 我忏悔
I do. I do.
我曾经无视神
I have looked past God.
我曾经骄傲并且自负
I have been proud, and I have been conceited.
我曾经是暴力和仇恨的使节
I have been an ambassador for violence and hate.
那都过去了
That is past.
重要的是你现在选择成为什么人
What matters is who you now choose to be.
你准备好了吗?
Are you ready?
你信仰在十字架上死去
Do you believe in Jesus Christ, the son of God,
又在第三天死而复生的
who died on the cross
神之子 耶稣基督吗?
and rose again on the third day?
我信仰
I do.
那么以圣父
Then in the name of the Father
圣子 圣灵之名
and of the Son and of the Holy Spirit,
我为你受洗
I baptize you.
所以这是真的!
Then it is true!
通往毁灭的门很宽
For wide is the gate and broad is the road
路很广阔
that leads to destruction,
许多人进入其中
and many enter through it.
通往生活的门
And small is the gate
却很小 路很狭窄
and narrow the road that leads to life.
仅有一小部分人找到了它
And only a few find it.
玛利亚
Mary.
我答应过大比大不会让她死去
I promised Tabitha I wouldn't let her die.
我以为我的信念足够
I thought my faith would be enough.
她多么善良
She was so sweet
找到耶稣是多么开心
and so happy to have found Jesus.
我要对她的死负责
I'm responsible for her death.
你无需负责
You are not responsible.
这是神的意志
It is God's will.
你可以跟我去看看她吗?
Will you come and see her?
别害怕
Don't be afraid.
这是彼得 我跟你们说过的那个人
This is Peter, the man I told you about.
玛利亚 你跟他们说了我什么?
What did you tell them about me, Mary?
我告诉了他们真相
I told them the truth.
你为什么把我带到这儿来?
And why have you brought me here?
因为我相信你可以帮她
Because I believe you can help her.
就这样!
Yes!
大比大!
Tabitha!
醒来吧!
Get up!
太好了!
Yes!
他治好了大比大!
He cured Tabitha!
彼得
Peter.
彼得 谢谢你 谢谢你
Peter, thank you. Thank you.
必须给这座城市一个教训
This city must be taught a lesson.
史诗
没有人能够逃脱
No one would escape.
难以忘怀
我们因为信念联合在一起
We are united in faith
大结局
把他们全都杀了
Kill them all.
别害怕
Don't be afraid.